Altschuller Papers
Altschuller Papers
1857-1984
1922-1980
Altschuller, Gregory, 1895-1983
1.2 linear feet
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Coller Rare Book Reading Room.
For related materials consult the Library's Portrait Catalog and Card Catalog.
Historical Note
Dr. Gregory Altschuller (1895-1983) was born in Russia and received his medical degree in Prague. He moved to the United States in 1938, where he was an internist at the Roosevelt Hospital and a fellow of the New York Academy of Medicine. His father, Dr. Isaac Altschuller (1870-1943), was a Russian physician specializing in tuberculosis. While living in the Crimea, he was a personal physician to Anton Chekhov and Leo Tolstoy.
Scope and Content
The collection documents the lives and work of Dr. Gregory Altschuller and his father Dr. Isaac Altschuller. The collection contains articles, reprints, typescripts, novels, and biographical materials. Of particular interest are accounts of Dr. Isaac Altschuller's experiences with Tolstoy and Dr. Gregory Altschuller's memories as a child in the house of Chekhov. Many documents are photocopies.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Medicine -- Russia -- History; Tolstoy, Leo, graf, 1828-1910; Chekhov, A. P. (Anton Pavlovich), 1860-1904; Altschuller, Isaac Naumovich, 1870-1943
Container List
- Isaac Altschuller, Series 1
  - Biographical Materials, undated, 1882-1938. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoirs of Leo Tolstoy, undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photo of Isaac Altschuller and Leo Tolstoy and related materials, undated, 1977-1978. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Gregory Altschuller, Series 2
  - Biographical Materials, 1939-1982. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Papers, Articles and Reprints, 1922-1929. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Papers, Articles and Reprints, 1930-1939. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Papers, Articles and Reprints, 1956, 1967, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Papers, Articles and Reprints, undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bezdomnye, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Uprooted, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Uprooted, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tzar I doctor related materials (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Delo Tveritinova related materials (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Early Arab Science and Scientists, undated, 1857, 1979-1980. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tzar I doctor, 1951. (Box 1)
  - Delo Tveritinova, 1963. (Box 1)
Provenance
Donated by Gregory Altschuller, date unknown.